Finding Aid for Department of Women’s Studies (University of Michigan) records, 1972-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Women’s Studies (University of Michigan) records 1972-2006, 1972-1999
University of Michigan. Department of Women’s Studies.
1 oversize folders
8.5 linear feet (in 10 boxes)
91431 Bimu C26 2
The collection of the Women's Studies Program at the University of Michigan contains administrative files, correspondence, historical information, curriculum information, and meeting minutes. The collection documents the founding of the program and the 1979 review of the program.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Department of Women’s Studies in 1990 (Donor # 7836 ). A second accession was received in 2009.
The Department of Women’s Studies records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Department of Women’s Studies record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 10
The movement to establish a women's studies program at the University of Michigan began in the summer of 1972. With funding from the offices of the Women's Advocate and the Advocate for Educational Innovation, Lydia Kleiner, a graduate student in the American Culture program, called together an ad hoc Committee for Women's Studies composed of about twenty students, faculty, staff, and community women. The committee drafted a proposal for a women's studies program, the objectives of which were to foster research and teaching on women and to assist the university in reexamining its curricula; the women active in promoting a women's studies program contended that the existing curricula distorted or ignored the contributions and roles of women.
The proposal was approved by the executive committee of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts in the spring of 1973 to be implemented in the fall of that year. In the meantime, a group of faculty and graduate students volunteered their services to teach the pilot course "Introduction to Women's Studies" (Women's Studies 240), which was first offered in fall term 1972. In 1975 an undergraduate major in Women's Studies was approved. A Graduate Certificate Program was instituted in 1984.
As part of its effort to promote research in the area of women's studies, the program offered a course entitled "Research on Women," which produced a scholarly journal entitled University of Michigan Papers in Women's Studies, with class members serving as the editorial board. The publication was successively renamed Occasional Papers and Michigan Feminist Studies.
The program was initially run by a steering committee that emerged out of the Committee for Women's Studies and was composed of about fifteen members. Membership on the committee, which met weekly, was open to anyone interested in and willing to work for the program; most of the members were graduate students, together with a few faculty members and undergraduates. In 1977 the steering committee became the program committee. The committee was not self-consciously a collective until the late 1970s but the constitution adopted in 1973 reflected the efforts of those involved in the program to make it democratic and non-hierarchical. A new governance model implemented in 1986/87 reaffirmed the program's commitment to collective governance.
In its first years the program had a quarter-time director, Margaret (Peg) Lourie, who also served as half-time secretary. In 1975 the directorship was made a half-time, two-year position. It was filled by Louise Tilly beginning in 1975, Susan Contratto in 1977, and Margot Norris in 1979. In 1979/80 the program was reviewed by the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, with several important changes resulting. The directorship was changed to a directorial pool that would rotate each term, along with a half-time associate director. Furthermore, most courses had been taught by graduate student teaching assistants in the 1970s, but as a consequence of the review, teaching assistants were no longer permitted to teach 300-level courses and an effort was made to involve more faculty members in teaching.
By the late 1970s the program was struggling with the perception that it was marginal to the intellectual life of the university. Over the next decade the program sought increasingly to secure its credibility as an academic unit by establishing an undergraduate major in 1975 and a graduate certificate program in 1984. In 1989 a second internal and external review was undertaken at the request of the program.
In 1990, the program established a directorship and an elected executive committee, appointing Abigail Stewart as Director of the Women's Studies Program until 1995. Abigail Stewart was initially succeeded by Anne C. Herrmann (1995-1996), followed by Sidonie Smith (1996-2000), Pamela Trotman Reid (2001-2003), and Valerie Traub (2003-2007).
The program celebrated its 20th Anniversary in 1992. During 1995, the program established two joint PhD programs in Psychology & Women's Studies and English & Women's Studies, later adding a History & Women's Studies PhD program in 1999 and Sociology & Women's Studies PhD program in 2000. Also in 1995, the Institute for Research on Women and Gender (IRWG) grew out of the program to focus on research by facilitating scholarship and disseminating important findings to the academic and public communities. The program underwent a Program Enhancement Initiative in 1998, allowing the program to initiate position requests and make tenured appointments and then move to its current home at Lane Hall in 2000. In July, 2007, the Women's Studies Program became the Department of Women's Studies, maintaining Valerie Traub as Chair of the Department (2007-2009), succeeded by Elizabeth Cole (2010-current).
In addition to teaching activities, the program established the Women's Studies library in 1979. During the mid-1990s, the library underwent financial difficulties, causing significant changes including selling or withdrawing parts of its collections. The library restructured in 1997, but ultimately was re-named the Women's Studies Reading Room and Resource Center and integrated with the department into Lane Hall. In addition to the library, the program produced a monograph series in conjunction with the University of Michigan Press called the Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender during the 1980s and 1990s. To better promote the series, the program created the Hamilton Prize Competition, which published the winning proposal in the series.
The collection of the Department of Women's Studies (formerly Women's Studies Program) at the University of Michigan contains a range of records, including administrative files, correspondence, curriculum information, event files, and meeting minutes. The collection documents the founding of the program, program reviews, the Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender series, the Women's Studies Library, and other program activities.
The records were received in two accessions. The original accession records consist of ten series, which are arranged in alphabetical order with the exception of the last, Miscellaneous. Records from the 2009 accession are arranged into seven series: Dean's Office, Executive Committee, Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender, Program Documents, Publications, Women's Studies Library, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Department of Women’s Studies.; University of Michigan. Women's Studies Program.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women's studies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Committees
  Committees (1972-1984, 0.75 feet), consists of fairly complete minutes, as well as some correspondence, of the Committee for Women's Studies, the Steering Committee, and the Program Committee. Also included are scattered material of other miscellaneous committees and minutes of marathon meetings, held at the beginning of each term to discuss short- and long-range planning and committee work. The steering and program committee minutes reflect the program's interest not simply in academic matters but in wider political issues, such as gay rights and sexual assault.
  - Committee for Women's Studies
    - Minutes and correspondence
      - May-August 1972 (Box 1)
      - September-December 1972 (Box 1)
      - 1973 undated (Box 1)
    - Program Proposal July 1972 (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee
    - Minutes
      - 1972-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - January-August 1977 (Box 1)
  - Program Committee
    - Minutes
      - September-December 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982 (Box 1)
      - 1983 (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Program Structure 1981 (Box 1)
  - Marathon Meetings
    - October 29, 1975 (Box 1)
    - January 10, 1976 (Box 1)
    - September 25, 1976 (Box 1)
    - January 22, 1977 (Box 1)
    - September 10, 1977 (Box 1)
    - January 14, 1978 (Box 1)
    - September 16, 1978 (Box 1)
    - January 13, 1979 (Box 1)
    - September 15, 1979 (Box 1)
    - January 19, 1980 (Box 1)
    - September 13, 1980 (Box 1)
    - September 19, 1980 (Box 1)
    - January 17, 1981 (Box 1)
    - September 19, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Gender Studies/Committee for Gender Research 1980-1981, undated (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Development Committee 1980 (Box 1)
  - Hiring Committee 1978-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Occasional Papers 1978-1979, undated (Box 1)
- Constitution circa 1972-1982
  Constitution (1973-1982 1 folder,) includes the original constitution adopted in 1973 and subsequent revisions up to 1982.
  - Constitution circa 1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (1971-1984, 0.5 feet), arranged chronologically, consists largely of requests for information about the University of Michigan's women's studies program from students wishing to pursue study in the field and from other institutions working to establish women's studies programs. In addition, there are scattered letters in the early 1970s from individuals seeking information on a variety of practical matters, reflecting the paucity of resources for persons seeking information on issues of concern to women.
  - 1971-1978, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - 1979-1984 undated, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Curriculum
  The Curriculum (1974-1981, 0.6 feet) series includes the curriculum committee minutes, course materials, and information related to the 1981 revision of the program's curriculum. Director's Reports to the Dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (1977-1981, 0.1 feet) provides useful overviews of the program's functioning from 1975 through 1981. Grant Files (1972-1981, 0.3 feet), arranged in rough chronological order, includes both funded and rejected grant applications, as well as related material. Related material includes efforts to develop the program, the areas of research the program wished to pursue and the lines along which the program wished to develop. While many of the grant files relate to teaching and curriculum development, projects such as the women's studies consortium lecture series demonstrate the program's desire to serve a broad constituency and to promote ties with the larger community outside the university.
  - Committee: Minutes
    - 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Courses
    - Notes for history of courses taught in Women's Studies 1972-1980 (Box 2)
    - Women's Studies 240 (pilot): course evaluation, Fall 1972 (Box 2)
    - Women's Studies 350 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Revision: 1981
    - Early drafts (Box 2)
    - December 1981 draft (Box 2)
    - Final version (Box 2)
    - Reading lists for 340 series (Box 2)
- Director's Reports to the Dean 1977-1981
  - Reports to Dean (Box 2)
- Grant files
  - Funded grant proposals
    - Curriculum Development Project (National Endowment for the Humanities)
      - Advisory Board Minutes 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 2)
      - Final Report November 30, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Overview (Box 2)
      - Proposal 1976 (Box 2)
      - Publications
        - Women's Art and Culture (1977) (Box 2)
        - New Woman, New World: The American Experience (1977) (Box 2)
    - Innovative Teaching Grants (Center for Research on Learning and Teaching) 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Women and Work Project
      - Proposal 1975 (Box 2)
      - Workshop 1976 (Box 2)
    - Women's Studies Consortium Lecture Series
      - Correspondence 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Final report October 31, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Proposals 1976 (Box 2)
      - Publicity 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      - Regrant agreement October 1976 (Box 2)
  - Rejected grant proposals (Box 3)
    - Innovative Teaching Grants (Center for Research on Learning and Teaching) 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Educational Equity for Women in the Health Professions (U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare) 1976 (Box 3)
    - Sex Role Stereotyping and Socialization to Sex Roles: Training Modules for Secondary Teachers (U.S. Office of Education) 1976 (Box 3)
    - Curriculum Project to Expand Vocational Choice (Charles Stewart Mott Foundation) 1978 (Box 3)
    - Two Interdisciplinary Conferences on Mothering and Childcare (Rockefeller Foundation) 1979 (Box 3)
    - Programs on Women's Issues in Humanistic Perspective (Michigan Council for the Humanities) 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1976, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
- Program Reviews
  Program Reviews (1974-1980, 0.5 feet) consists for the most part of materials documenting the 1979/80 review of the program by the College of LS&A, along with a small amount of material on the 1974 review. Special Events (1973-1981, 0.1 feet) includes minutes and correspondence of the Speakers Committee concerning lecturers who were brought to campus by the program as well as fliers and other publicity material for guest speakers and special events. Student Organizations (1979-1980, .05 feet,) is a very thin series consisting of a few items relating to two women's studies organizations.
  - 1974 (Box 3)
  - 1979-1980
    - Agreement with the Dean (Box 3)
    - Charge to the Review Committee 1979 (Box 3)
    - Coalition to Save Women's Studies 1980 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Documentation submitted (Box 3)
    - Faculty questionnaire (Box 3)
    - Letters of support (Box 3)
    - Progress report December 1980 (Box 3)
    - Proposed guidelines (Box 3)
    - Report of the Review Committee (Box 3)
    - Schedules (Box 3)
    - Teaching Assistants, Supervision of (Box 3)
    - Women's Studies Program response to Review Committee's report (Box 3)
- Special Events
  - Speakers Committee: Correspondence 1973-1981, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Events 1977-1981, undated, 6 folders (Box 3)
- Student Organizations
  - Undergraduate Women's Studies Organization (Box 3)
  - Women's Programming Collective 1979-1980 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous (1974-1990, 0.1 feet) series includes orientation manuals, a survey of women's studies students, library materials, and event fliers.
  - Library 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Memoranda and fliers 1978-1981, undated (Box 3)
  - Orientation Manual, Fall 1990 (Box 3)
  - Publicity survey 1974 (Box 3)
  - Questionnaire and responses on attitudinal changes in Women's Studies 200 (by Jane Leu) 1978 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Assistants 1976-1980, undated (Box 3)
- Dean's Office
  Dean's Office (1995-1998, 0.1 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and contains correspondence of the Dean's Office as well as search criteria for an Afroamerican Women's Studies faculty member. Executive Committee (1994-2000, 0.1 linear feet) consists of the meeting minutes of the Executive Committee arranged chronologically.
  - Center for Afroamerican & African Studies and Women's Studies Professor Search 1995 (Box 10)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
  - Correspondence 1994-2000 (Box 10)
- Executive Committee
  - Agenda and Meeting Minutes 1994-2000, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender
  Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender (1976-1994, 1.3 linear feet) is divided into four sub-series, arranged alphabetically: Editorial Advisory Committee, Hamilton Prize Competition, Program Documents, and Proposals. The Editorial Advisory Committee (1986-1994, 0.1 feet), Hamilton Prize Competition (1983-1989, 15 feet), Program Documents (1980-1991, .05 feet) sub-series consist of meeting minutes of the Editorial Advisory Committees for the Critical Perspective Series and the Hamilton Prize Competition, correspondence, and published series lists. The Proposals sub-series (1986-1994, 1 linear foot) consists of all correspondence, CVs, judge evaluations, and proposals for the Critical Perspectives on Women and Gender Series by proposed author.
  - Editorial Advisory Committee
    - Agendas 1987-1994, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Critical Perspectives Procedures Correspondence 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - D'Arms and UM Press Executive Committee Correspondence 1986-1990 (Box 4)
    - E-mail Proposal Evaluations 1994 (Box 4)
    - Inter-board Correspondence 1989-1992 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1986-1994, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Hamilton Prize Competition
    - Abstract Lists 1984-1986 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1976-1987, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Editorial Advisory Committee Members and Addresses 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Editorial Advisory Committee Minutes 1979-1989, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Hamilton Judges 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Publication and Prize Lists 1982-1985 (Box 4)
    - Reader's Reports 1988 (Box 4)
  - Program Documents
    - Correspondence with Authors 1987-1990 (Box 4)
    - Description of Series 1991 (Box 4)
    - Feminist Theatre Groups Undated (Box 4)
    - List of Scholars Contacted for Series 1988 (Box 4)
    - Publications List 1980-1990 (Box 4)
    - Published Series Lists 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - Series Announcements 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Women's Alliances for Social Change 1988 (Box 4)
  - Proposals
    - Arat, Yesim 1992 (Box 4)
    - Aries, Elizabeth 1994 (Box 4)
    - Bell, Susan and Marilyn Yalom 1986 (Box 4)
    - Bourque, Susan: Correspondence 1987-1990 (Box 4)
    - Bourque, Susan: Proposal and CV 1988 (Box 4)
    - Burkett, Elinor C. 1984 (Box 4)
    - Buss, Fran Leeper 1988 (Box 4)
    - Campbell, Jacquelyn 1988 (Box 4)
    - Candib, Lucy 1988 (Box 4)
    - Chai, Alice Yun 1987 (Box 4)
    - Crosby, Faye and Susan Clayton: Correspondence 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Crosby, Faye and Susan Clayton: Proposal and CV 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Da Rocha Lima, Valentina 1990 (Box 4)
    - Dawson, Ruth 1988 (Box 4)
    - DeLauretis, Teresa 1990 (Box 4)
    - DeShazer, Mary 1985 (Box 4)
    - Dickeman, Mildred 1987 (Box 4)
    - Doane, Janice and Devon Hodges: Correspondence 1987-1991 (Box 4)
    - Doane, Janice and Devon Hodges: Proposal and CV 1989 (Box 4)
    - Dolan, Jill 1991 (Box 4)
    - Durham, Carolyn 1988 (Box 4)
    - Ebert, Teresa 1990-1993, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Feldman, Roberta 1991 (Box 4)
    - Fine, Michelle: Correspondence 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Fine, Michelle: Proposal and CV 1990 (Box 4)
    - Fonow, Mary Margaret and Judith A. Cook 1986 (Box 4)
    - Friedman, Jane 1984 (Box 4)
    - Gabriel, Ayala 1994 (Box 4)
    - Gole, Nilufer 1991 (Box 4)
    - Gordon, Deborah 1991 (Box 4)
    - Gossy, Mary: Freudian Slips 1994 (Box 4)
    - Gossy, Mary: Spanish Golden Age 1988 (Box 4)
    - Hansen, Karen T. 1988 (Box 4)
    - Hoff, Lee Ann 1988 (Box 4)
    - Holland, Endesha Ida Mae 1986 (Box 4)
    - Hornstein, Gail 1988 (Box 4)
    - Huh, Joonok 1988 (Box 4)
    - Hurtado, Aida 1992 (Box 4)
    - Keating, Ann Louise 1994 (Box 4)
    - Malone, Carolyn 1994 (Box 4)
    - Malson, Michelene 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - Marshall, Nancy 1986 (Box 4)
    - McDonnell, Jane 1986 (Box 4)
    - Messer-Davidow, Ellen 1994 (Box 5)
    - Miller, Christanne 1990 (Box 5)
    - Moore, Henrietta undated (Box 5)
    - Morawski, Jill: Correspondence 1988 (Box 5)
    - Morawski, Jill: Proposal and CV 1990 (Box 5)
    - Moscovici, Claudia 1993 (Box 5)
    - Newton, Judith: Correspondence 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - Newton, Judith: Proposal and CV 1988-1990 (Box 5)
    - Passerini, Luisa 1989 (Box 5)
    - Proposals, various, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Roberts, Robin 1986 (Box 5)
    - Robertson, Jennifer 1991 (Box 5)
    - Schapiro, Miriam 1988 (Box 5)
    - Scheper-Hughes, Nancy 1987 (Box 5)
    - Schulz, Amy J. 1994 (Box 5)
    - Schwarzenback, Sibyl: Correspondence 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - Schwarzenback, Sibyl: Proposal and CV 1989 (Box 5)
    - Spiganesi, Angelyn 1987 (Box 5)
    - Squier, Susan 1988 (Box 5)
    - Stolcke, Verena 1987 (Box 5)
    - Stoper, Emily 1986 (Box 5)
    - Warren, Carol A.B. 1984 (Box 5)
    - White, E. Frances 1984 (Box 5)
    - Wright, Barbara D. 1986 (Box 5)
- Program Documents
  The Program Documents (1978-2005, 2 linear feet) series surveys the activities of the Women's Studies Department and consists of five sub-series arranged alphabetically: Alumni, Committee on Institutional Cooperation, Conferences & Events, Historical Documents, and Projects. Alumni (2002, 0.1 feet) contains survey results of alumni regarding their experience of the women's studies department and its impact on their careers. Committee on Institutional Cooperation (1986-1988, 0.25 feet) details meetings of Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC)'s women's studies division and contains information comparing women's studies departments across the United States. Conferences & Events (1986-2005, 0.75 feet) includes event planning documents and speaker correspondence. Historical Documents (1978-1999, 0.2 feet) includes materials not included in the original accession, including the proposals for establishing a women's studies certificate, and 1989 program review and contract modification with the U. S. Department of Education. The sub-series also contains materials relating to the 1999 Program Enhancement Initiative. Projects (1986-1996, 0.7 feet) consists of correspondence, reports, and other records relating to departmental projects such as Differences Among Women, Feminist Practice, Feminist Scholarship, Women's Initiative Group, and Women of Color projects.
  - Alumni
    - Alumni Questionnaire 2002, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation
    - Correspondence 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Documents 1985 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Documents 1989 (Box 5)
    - Directory 1987 (Box 5)
    - Meeting Documents 1986-1988, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Syllabi 1986 (Box 5)
    - Women's Studies Programs Questionnaire 1985 (Box 5)
  - Conferences and Events
    - Event Files
      - 20th Birthday Celebration 1992 (Box 5)
      - ACLU Conference: Women & Girls, the Law, and Social Change 2003 (Box 5)
      - Angela Davis Lecture 2003 (Box 5)
      - Beijing, China Conference 1995 (Box 5)
      - Black History Month 1988-1991 (Box 5)
      - Brownbags 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Co-sponsorships 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Co-sponsorships Promises List 2004-2005 (Box 6)
      - Faculty Seminar 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Gender, Power, and Representation Theme Semester, Winter 2002, 2001-2002 (Box 6)
      - Gender and Society Film Series 1991 (Box 6)
      - Goethe Institute 1989-1992 (Box 6)
      - Goethe Institute: Germany Conference 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Jewish Woman Writing Feminism 2004 (Box 6)
      - Judith Herman Lecture 1991-1992 (Box 6)
      - Lane Hall Opening Dedication Events 2000 (Box 6)